American Philosophical Society Archives 1743-1984 APS.Archives
American Philosophical Society
- Wistar Association, 1818-1968; XIII; 4.5 ln. ft.
  Composed originally of eight members of the APS, the Wistar Association was organized in 1818 to continue the agreeable social entertainments which the Society's late President Caspar Wistar had held regularly for many years for members and distinguished visitors to the city. The Association suspended meetings during the Civil War, and did not meet after 1866. In 1884 the Fortnightly Club was formed for purposes similar to those of the old Wistar Association, although not all of its members were also members of the APS. When the Fortnightly sought to change its name to the Wistar Club, two ancient survivors of the older group revived the association, elected new members, and absorbed the upstart. In 1898, membership in APS was restored as a prerequisite for election. The Association has met regularly since 1886. Its membership is now over twenty, and modern transportation has made it feasible to include persons not residents of Philadelphia.
  - Manuscript archives, 1818-1910; XIII.1; 1.0 vol.; Wistar Association
    Contains a copy of the 1842 constitution; miscellaneous minutes; membership lists; memoranda and receipts; and letters, principally of acceptance and resignation, from such persons as Franklin Bache, John C. Cresson, Jacob M. Da Costa, Robley Dunglinson, Robert Hare, John Kintzing Kane, William M. Meredith, William Pepper, Moncure Robinson, and George Sharswood.
    Deposited by the Association, 1911.
  - Annual lists of the Wistar Party, 1824-42; XIII.2; 2.0 vols.; Wistar Association
  - Scrapbook, "Sketch of the Wistar Party", ca. 1804-1861; XIII.3; 1.0 vol.; Wistar Association
    Isaac M. Hays' copy of Sketch of the Wistar Party of Philadelphia (Philadelphia, 1846), with interleaved additions such as a letter of Wistar's lists of members, announcements, invitations, etc.
  - Scrapbook, "Sketch of the Wistar Party", ca. 1898-1925; XIII.4; 1.0 vol.; Wistar Association
    1898 edition of Sketch of the Wistar Party of Philadelphia that includes letters of Henry C. Lea, lists of members, announcements, newspaper clippings, etc.
  - Correspondence, 1925-1968; XIII.5; 2.0 boxes (1 ln. ft.); Wistar Association
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.; XIII.6; 2.0 boxes (1 ln. ft.); Wistar Association
    Includes invitations, engravings, etc.
  - The Centenary of the Wistar Party. An historical address, by Hampton L. Carson, 1918; XIII.7; 1.0 vol. (36 pp.); Wistar Association
    Includes two letters from Carson to I. M. Hays.
  - History of the Wistar Association, 1945; XIII.8; 1.0 vol. (27 pp.); Wistar Association
    Joseph Stokes' copy, from 1957. Included is a page of notes in his hand, for a talk he gave before the Association.
  - Fortnightly Club. Minutes, 1884-1887; XIII.9; 1.0 vol.
    Deposited by the Wistar Association, 1911.